## Slim Ouertani June-81, Tunisian

ouertani@gmail.com • (00966)-(0)-583012381 • Riyadh (Saudi Arabia) linkedin.com/in/ouertani • ouertani.github.io • jroller.com/ouertani • twitter.com/ouertani

## Architect, InfoQ Fr Editor Founder & Organiser of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA Certified Trainer Togaf, Archimate, PMP, Spring, Java, Cmmi, ITIL, Mongo, Scala

## Summary

Slim Ouertani is solution architect, InfoQ-Fr editor, Big Data Science, Cloud and SOA Certified trainer , founder and organizer of Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup. After his engineer's degree in computer science, Slim spent over than 10 years in multinational companies such as Orange, Sagem and STMicroelectronics as architect, international agile coach and Head of IT development department. His main role was to build, design and collaborate in the development of enterprise solutions.

Slim regularly contributes to InfoQ-FR community where he is the author of many articles and news. you to follow him on twitter @ouertani.

He's broad certified as in addition to his SOA, Cloud and Big Data Science certifications: Trainer, Architect & Engineer, Slim holds multiple certifications including Togaf 9, Archimate 2, PMP, ITIL, CMMi, Mongo, Spring, JAVA, SCALA and reactive programming...

Trained as an architect, Slim specializes in enterprise Java development, functional programming focusing on highly scalable applications and now expanding his experience to cloud computing.

Slim enjoys open source contribution and invite

## Experience

### Al-Elm Information Security

#### **Solution Architect**

RIYADH, SAUDI ARABIA 06-2014 - present

- Member/Founder of ELM Development Architecture Center of Excellence.
- EPG committee member, responsible of the architecture models, oversee the process architecture, approve it and ensuring the process improvement.
- Architecting and Designing enterprise solutions using diverse technology stack
  Work with peers to conduct Solution Architecture Reviews for a broad set of projects
- Review and provide input into functional & non-functional requirements
  Provide consulting and conduct reviews through the development lifecycle
- Defining the Architecture and guiding the use of various tools, technologies and techniques in the realization of that Architecture
- Create and maintain a set of standard practices, patterns and anti-patterns and ensure the appropriate usage of that.

## Sofrecom (Orange FT Group)

Tunis, Tunisia 03-2013 - 06-2014

## Software Architect, International Agile Coach

- Manage and direct virtual distributed teams
- Make or Buy Analysis
- Establish regular meetings to review technical designs and provide mentoring and guidance
- Mentor development teams on different architecture and design paradigms or practices
- Maintain a knowledge base of emerging technologies and products
- Scrum Master, Enterprise Architect, Apache Camel, Spring
  CXF, Spring Batch, Atomikos, ActiveMq, Jonas, hibernate

## Zenika

Paris, FRANCE

12-2012 - 03-2013

**JEE Architect** 

• Client: Bouygues Telecom

- Project: Home Automation (2 months)
- BBox embedded automation solution communicating with centralized system

  - Embedded: OSGI, REST server/client, Raspberry pi- Server: Fuse ESB, CXF, Camel, Spring, Jax-Rs, Osgi, Maven
- Client: SwissPost
- Project: Image Plus (2 months)
- Online outsourcing solution for picture processing.
  - Scrum, Kanban, Jenkies, Git, Cloudbees, Maven

- MVP, Spring 3.1, GWT 2.5, JPA 2

Orange Tunis, Tunisia

#### **Head of Development and Tools Manager**

01-2010 - 11-2012

- JEE 6, MDB, JPA, Scala, Wicket, Play, J2ME, Spring ROO, WS, Glassfish, Talend, Birt
- Development and implementation of a web service platform :

JEE 6, SCALA, EJB 3.1, JAX-WS, Oracle, JPA

- IN/AIR, BSCS/CMS/Data Charging/CRM/IVR/USSD
   Development of the "after sales service" solution: Play 1.2.x, groovy, jquery
   Launch of BI project: Talend, Birt, Oracle
   Bulk SMS: Wicket, JEE 6, JPA, Postgres

- Unbarring SMS: J2ME, JAX-WS, MDB, JPA
- Different applications: inter systems and synchronization platforms, web application...

#### Sagem Software & Technologies

Tunis, Tunisia

#### **Solution Architect**

06-2009 - 01-2010

- · Architecture design and integration of a communication server and administration of remote gateways.
  - JEE, JMS, Spring, GWT, AndroMda, Hibernate, SMSJboss, ActiveMq, MDA

03-2008 - 06-2009**Solution Architect** 

- Modular OSGi Server architecture under Linux platform responsible for controlling and interacting with electricity counters in order to retrieve statistics and have data storing/manipulation via different technologies and frameworks
  - OSGI, SCA, Spring DM, JAX-WS, JPA, GPRS, GSM/DATA, SMS, SNMP4j, Hessian, Ftp, Equinox, JETTY, POSTGRESOL
  - DISTRIBUTED COMPUTING, Cryptography

#### Solution Architect & Team Leader

12-2007 - 03-2008

- Designing an SOA architecture and implementation of an Intranet service for human resources using liferay portal.
  - JEE5, EJB3, JAX-WS, JSF, PORTLET, JPA, SOA
- GLASSFISH V2, TOMCAT6, LIFERAY 4.4, POSTGRESQL

**STMicroelectronics** Tunis, Tunisia

02-2006 - 12-2007Coordinator • Implementing Intranet tools used for monitoring the evolution of validation campaigns.

- J2EE, JSF, Hibernate/JPA, JAXB/JAXP, Design Pattern
- TOMCAT 5.5, POSTGRESQL

Developer 12-2005 - 02-2006

- Validating processors and compilers under different platforms.
  - Linux, Solaris, Cygwin, Mingwin, Perl, Shell

**GL TRADE** Tunis, Tunisia

#### Developer & designer

08-2005 - 12-2005

- GL TACTICS: A trader module enhancing the efficiency of the negotiating teams giving them the possibility to customize the implementation strategies and accelerate the decision process.
  - C++, Design Pattern

Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of work experiences along with recommendations.

#### Certificate

Big Data Science Engineer, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 08-2016Big Data Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 05-2016Archimate Certified, Open GroupSCORE 82%, 02-2016Archimate Foundation, Open GroupSCORE 97%, 02-2016Cloud Trainer, Arcitura10-2015Cloud Architect, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 10-2015Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupSCORE 90%, 06-2015ITIL Foundation, ExinSCORE 95%, 06-2015	Big Data Science Trainer, Arcitura	09-2016
Archimate Certified, Open GroupSCORE 82%, 02-2016Archimate Foundation, Open GroupSCORE 97%, 02-2016Cloud Trainer, Arcitura10-2015Cloud Architect, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 10-2015Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupSCORE 90%, 06-2015	Big Data Science Engineer, Arcitura	With Honors, 08-2016
Archimate Foundation, Open GroupScore 97%, 02-2016Cloud Trainer, Arcitura10-2015Cloud Architect, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 10-2015Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupScore 90%, 06-2015	Big Data Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 05-2016
Cloud Trainer, Arcitura10-2015Cloud Architect, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 10-2015Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupScore 90%, 06-2015	Archimate Certified, Open Group	Score 82%, 02-2016
Cloud Architect, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 10-2015Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupScore 90%, 06-2015	Archimate Foundation, Open Group	Score 97%, 02-2016
Cloud Professional, ArcituraWITH HONORS, 09-2015Togaf Certified, Open GroupScore 90%, 06-2015	Cloud Trainer, Arcitura	10-2015
Togaf Certified, Open Group Score 90%, 06-2015	Cloud Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 10-2015
	Cloud Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 09-2015
ITIL Foundation, Exin Score 95%, 06-2015	Togaf Certified, Open Group	Score 90%, 06-2015
	ITIL Foundation, Exin	Score 95%, 06-2015

Togaf Foundation, Open Group	Score 95%, 04-2015
Project Management Professional, PMI	03-2015
SOA Trainer, Arcitura	01-2015
SOA Architect, Arcitura	With Honors, 12-2014
SOA Professional, Arcitura	With Honors, 11-2014
Introduction to Cmmi for development, Cmmi Institute	09-2014
Entrepreneurship for all, EFFECTUATION, EMLYON	Score 75,8%, 01-2014
Principles of Reactive Programming, Coursera	Score 97.5%, 01-2014
MongoDB for DBAs, MongoDB	Score 94%, 11-2013
MongoDb for java, MongoDb	Score 95%, 10-2013
Spring Framework 3, Pivotal	Score 94%, 02-2013
Java 6 Programmer Certified Professional, Oracle	Score 100%, 08-2012
Team Performance, STMicroelectronics	04-2007
English, British Council	4B, 02-2007
GL Certified Professional, GL TRADE	09-2005

#### **Education**

National School of Computer ScienceENSI	Tunis,Tunisia
Graduation Project in Computer Engineering	2005
National School of Computer Science ENSI	Tunis, Tunisia
Engineer Degree in Computer Science	2002 - 2005
Tunis Preparatory Institute for Engineering StudiesIPEIT	Tunis, Tunisia
Preparatory Courses (Math Sup, Math Spe)	2000 - 2002
Hannibal	Ariana, Tunisia
(Pre-university Secondary Education)	1994 - 2000

### **Other Activities**

#### InfoQ Fr Editor

http://www.infoq.com/fr/author/Slim-Ouertani

## Founder & Organizer

Riyadh IT Architecture Meetup

Paremus, SCA with OSGI, David Savage

http://www.meetup.com/Riyadh-IT-Architecture

#### **BLOGGGING**

http://java.dzone.com/users/slim.ouertani

http://ouertani.github.io

http://www.jroller.com/ouertani

http://twitter.com/ouertani

#### **MAGAZINE**

From Microservices to SOA - 20.07.2015 Service Technology Magazine - Issue XCI http://servicetechmag.com/I91/0715-1

# STAMPLE

07.02.2009

https://stample.co Scala, Akka, Play

**INTERVIEW** 

http://www.prosyst.com/

http://goo.gl/H5yJzY

ElasticSearch, MongoDb, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

## **OPEN SOURCE**

https://github.com/ouertani http://www.reactive-streams.org

#### **Arcitura Authorized Training Partner**

http://www.arcitura.com/ Big Data Science, Cloud & SOA

### **Computer Skills**

Architecture Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor

EA Togaf, Archimate, Sparx

Design Functional programming, EA, UML, Design Pattern, MVC, MDA, OO, MVP

Architecture Microservices, Reactive, N-tiers, SOA, SCA, Actor

Cloud Bees, Heroku, App Engine, Amazon S3, GreenCloud

Agile Scrum, Kanban

CollaborationTrello, Slack, Github, Codex, Wiki, Sharepoint, IceScrum, Bugzilla

Written & Spoken

Training	
Project Management Professional, PMP	11.2014 08.2009 01.2009
OSGi design pattern : White board & Extender  By: Slim Ouertani	
SCA architecture with Newton  By: David Savage & Mike Francis	
OSGi, architecture and environment  By: Roman Roelofsen	05.2008
Publications	
Pour le fun: for-comprehension à la sauce Java 8	23.07.2015
Vrais ou Faux Jumeaux ?	25.11.2014
Curryfication Java: methods & fonctions	29.07.2014
Des Lenses en Java ?	30.06.2014
Barboter dans le compilateur Java	02.06.2014
Mon Trampoline avec Java 8	18.04.2014
Démystifier les iteratees avec Java	01.11.2013
Le Trio : Akka, Spring et Scala	16.10.2013
Rest with Scala and Vert.x	18.02.2013
Fun with Scala and Vert.x	11.02.2013
Getting Started with Play 2.1 , Scala 2.10 and Slick 0.11.1	01.11.2012
Please refer to my Linked-in profile for a more complete list of publications since 2008.	
News	
Publication de la Nouvelle Spécification d'ArchiMate 3.0	22.06.2016
Java EE et les Anges Gardiens	11.05.2016
Microservice antipatterns à Qcon London 2016	14.04.2016
MongoDB: la magie des Reactive-Streams avec les Capped Collections	21.05.2015
Publication de l'API Reactive Streams 1.0	07.05.2015
Docker, le dernier clou dans le cercueil des serveurs d'applications Java ?	19.03.2015

Languages

Arabic, French English